Finding Aid for Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development records, 1954-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development records 1954-1972
Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development.
2 linear feet
851261 Bn 2
Reports, minutes, project files, and conference materials; also files relating to the visit of Japanese educators to the United States.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mr. Walker L. Cisler (Donor No. 5304 ) in September 1972.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development originated as a result of President Eisenhower's "Atoms for Peace" message delivered to the United Nations in 1953. The Fund was incorporated in 1954 as a nonprofit organization for the purpose of promoting worldwide cooperation on atomic energy matters, including nuclear science, engineering, industrial applications, nuclear economics, and law and public relations. Specifically, the Fund sought to identify areas within these fields not otherwise addressed by national or international governments, especially in matters of education and training.
The Board of Directors included Walker L. Cisler, President of the Detroit Edison Company, William C. Foster, Executive Vice President of Olin Mathieson Company, Oscar M. Ruebhausen of the New York Bar, Joseph M. Dodge of the Detroit Bank and Trust Company and E. Blythe Stason, Dean of the University of Michigan Law School. The Fund was initially supported financially by the Ford Foundation, the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, the Johnson Foundation, and the Thomas F. Peterson Foundation.
The Fund's programs involved a variety of activities including sponsorship of grants and fellowships for students from Italy, Austria, the Netherlands, Yugoslavia and Japan to study in the United States and abroad. The Fund also sponsored a group of visiting Japanese educators in the United States each year from 1964 to 1971. Projects included the Egyptian Radioisotope Center, the Carnegie International Exhibit in 1955, the University of Mexico-University of Michigan Fellowship Program, and missions to India, Pakistan, Turkey, Western Europe and South America. International conferences were held in Geneva in 1955, 1958, and 1964; in Brussels in 1956 and in Tokyo in 1957. The Fund was also involved in the development of similar funds in Austria, Belgium, Japan and Switzerland.
The Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development was dissolved in 1972.
The records of The Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development have been arranged into the following series: Administrative; Fund Projects; Other Funds; Western Europe Monthly Reports; Conferences; Publications; Grants and Fellowships; Japanese Educators in the United States; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Nuclear energy.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative 1954-1972
  The Administrative series, along with meeting reports, bylaws and vitae of the Board of Directors, contains general information and largely internal correspondence about the start up and planning for the Fund. There is also a folder containing the announcements of the Fund with responses and comments from a number of notable persons.
  - Incorporation/Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Announcement of Fund; Responses and Comments (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1954-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Directors and Officers (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 1954-1972 (Box 1)
  - Members Meetings Minutes 1954-1972 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes 1954-1971 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1955-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Fund Projects 1955-1958
  The Fund Projects series includes many of the diverse activities the Fund undertook: The University of Mexico-University of Michigan Fellowship Program, the Egyptian Radioisotope project, and missions to India, Turkey and Pakistan among others.
  - Austrian Mission 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Burma Laboratory 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie International Exhibit 1955 (Box 1)
  - Egyptian Radioisotope Center 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Hafstad Mission to India, Pakistan and Turkey 1955 (Box 1)
  - Pakistan Library 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy in Yugoslavia 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Republic of Turkey Program 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Sakae Shimizu visit to U.S. 1956 (Box 1)
  - South American Reports 1956 (Box 1)
  - University of Mexico-University of Michigan Fellowship 1955-1956 (Box 1)
- Other Funds
  - Austrian (Box 1)
  - Belgian (Box 1)
  - Japanese (Box 1)
  - Swiss (Box 1)
- Western Europe Monthly Reports
  - 1962-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Conferences 1955-1972
  - Geneva, 1st U.N. International Conference 1955 (Box 2)
  - Geneva, 2nd U.N. International Conference 1958 (Box 2)
  - Geneva, 3rd U.N. International Conference 1964 (Box 2)
  - Brussels 1956 (Box 2)
  - Tokyo 1971 (Box 2)
- Publications
  - Various titles (Box 2)
- Grants and Fellowships
  The Grants and Fellowships series includes information about students in the United States and abroad sponsored by the Fund along with persons given travel and research grants.
  - Japanese Students (background) 1957-1964 (Box 2)
  - Haiutaka Kimura (Box 2)
  - Masamitsu Kosaki (Box 2)
  - Hideaki Nishihara (Box 2)
  - Toshihides Takeshita (Box 2)
  - Akio Tojo (Box 2)
  - Kuniniko Uematsu (Box 2)
  - Floyd W. Bunt (Box 2)
  - Robert W.R. Dee (Box 2)
  - Isidor Hazan (Box 2)
  - Dr. Johann Korkisch (Box 2)
  - Michael Krichbaum (Box 2)
  - Giuliano Pinto (Box 2)
  - Marco Toaselli (Box 2)
  - Panayotis Tsilimigras (Box 2)
- Japanese Educators in the U.S.
  - Miscellaneous 1962-1972, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1 folders
  - Directors and Officers (Box 2)
  - 1st U.N. International Conference on Atomic Peace (Box 2)
  - Egyptian Radioisotope Project (Box 2)
  - Monthly Report October 1964 (Box 2)